[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
this is kanchan shreki for software
engineering radio
welcome to our show today on training
simulator apps
our guest today is atka nida atkar is
senior director of development
at bohemia interactive simulations or bi
sim
they create training simulators artka
joined bism
in 2009 before that he worked in the
gaming industry
welcome to our show today atka it's
great to have you here
is there anything else you'd like to add
to your bio before we get started
hi kanchen thank you for having me it is
very exciting to be
on this podcast i think you said all the
important things
now the director of development in
bohemian attractive simulations where we
do these
training simulators and i'm responsible
for all the development in all our
offices around the world let's get
started with an example of a game
and the simulation and then we'll
compare and contrast them
so there are of course many many games
we can choose from a lot of them
so there are simple ones like tetris for
example
you might have it on your on your phone
or some other different casual game that
you were playing when you were
somewhere in a train or bus the gaming
or the simulations that is a bit more
difficult to choose some
that would be known to people so i think
that
one example is flight simulator which is
i think somewhere on the border of
of the games and simulations it is a
pretty good simulator of flying
airplanes but it is being sold as a game
on the gaming platform on steam so you
can buy it as a game you can play it as
a game
but it is also a very very serious
simulator of flying
of course on my side i can put in our
simulator which is called vbs4
it is a simulator that is used is being
used for
training military personnel in many
different military
training cases there are of course other
simulations too
for especially for some special
machinery or again
flight simulators that are being used to
really train uh trained pilots
but of course there's not as many of
them as games so what about
the infrastructure so what about let's
talk about the gaming
engine is there a difference between the
engine for a game
versus a simulation
it is a bit difficult question but i
think to to be able to answer it i will
a bit
limit uh myself on when i'm talking
about game engines so
let's talk about the game engine that
you can get yourself
unreal or unity these engines you can
just basically get
whenever you want and you may want to
start to build a game on that
on the other hand we would have the
simulation engine which is
a bit much more than much more than
just the sandbox that you get with amul
and unity so
when you get yourself unreal or unity
you get as i said
sandbox and a set of very very nice
tools which you can use to
to build your game use them to create
either the 3d content or 2d content
you can use them to create some
scripting some functionality some
interaction
and that at the end forms your game on
the other hand the simulation engine
that is much more that is something that
is already prepared
to do some simulation and again for the
sake of this talk i will be talking
about training simulations so
of course you can have different type of
simulations of some
physics processes or so but i will be
talking about engines that are being
used for
simulating some kind of a training and i
will be mostly referring to the military
training because that's
where my expertise is so if you get a
simulation engine like that
you get a lot of functionality that you
can
start to use immediately to do some of
the training
if i should use some kind of analogy i
will use the one that
our ceo likes to use he compares this to
the situation when you're buying a log
house either you can just basically buy
a fully featured fully built fully
equipped
log house and move in and may and be
there or
that would be your simulation engine or
you can buy a piece of land
a set of power tools and a pile of
planks
and then you would just build the
lighthouse yourself that would be the
game engine value which is cats
unreal or unity so that would be the
kind of a difference in
how much is already there built to how
much you have to build
with yourself we'll drill a little bit
more into that in later sections and you
know what is the delta
but before we get to that can we also
discuss
how is developing these games or gaming
engines or even simulation engines
different from standard line of business
or web apps
i think i would like to answer that
basically in
every game or simulation development
there is
a bit of business of web application
development
where in the business and web
applications development very probably
is not much from the game's development
by that i'm trying to say that creating
a some
bit more complex game is a set of
really different kind of things you have
to do you have to think about
also a very low level stuff but if you
go a bit higher level
you can create user interface and these
days
these user interfaces are often used
or often built by using the technologies
that are being used to create apps
or like html and and all the frameworks
that are built upon that
so you have a bit of a web application
development there
games of course these days are using
databases
to store a lot of data that they need
about the players and about
about the characters that are inside so
again you have a bit of a databases
there which are
usually being used in the business
development so i would say that
there is a really like the gaming is a
very complex thing that has a very
broad reach of what needs to be done
but i think that uh business
applications might be more focused on
one specific thing
got it so the engine is more general
purpose
and when you're talking of simulation
engines there are additional features
and frameworks and
services that's correct the game engine
as such is a complex thing where you
have to just think about what kind of
hardware you use it for and these kind
of things
and we can talk about it maybe a bit a
bit later that's similar to simulation
engine
but then the more you want to just do
when you more you want to train
the more functionality you have to add
and the more
different let's say areas of expertise
you have to use and
then create the content for the training
so you hinted at that earlier but can
you
summarize the difference between the
goals of a game
and that of a simulation sure like for
the game
i think i don't want to just uh be too
generalized but i think that most of the
game or majority of the games
their goal is to entertain right to just
basically entertain you
to give you some kind of a feeling to
give you something you you enjoy
where the simulation is much more
serious especially when
as i said as i'm talking about training
simulations
it's about delivering training it's
about delivering some kind of skills or
training some kind of skills that you
will then use in the real life
maybe in the games you probably don't
have maybe you do
some kind of term of negative gaming but
in simulation training you have a term
that is called negative training
so the simulation if it delivers to you
something
that you would then learn wrongly and
use it wrongly in your real life
you for example in the case of military
simulations or military
industry you can cause a casualties well
with the games it's
more casual stuff and more about
feelings where the simulation is more
about
really training learning and delivering
some kind of skills training
so what are the most common industries
that invest heavily in simulations
as i'm working in a company that
delivers training simulators for
military i definitely would say that
militaries are very interested in
simulations
why because simulations save
time they save money a lot of it because
you don't have to for example use
ammunition right it's basically
simulated ammunition is for free
where the real life is very expensive it
saves paperwork
uh because if you want to just get out a
tank to to train with it
you have to fill in a lot of paperwork
where in the simulation you just
basically jump into the
tank and you can train with it so
definitely there is a lot of
interest in militaries for training
simulated training
but i think i already mentioned for
example the pilot trainers
pilots are being trained on very
specialized simulators
before they actually can can go into the
real plane
and i see like a surge of interest from
other
industries also like the first
responders and any kind of industries
using very complex
machinery that they like to basically
train these kind of skills before they
start to use the real thing so let's now
dig deeper into the challenges
of developing simulations versus game
and the differences
starting with the game engine
architecture
so what would you say are the common
components or
services or layers between gaming
engines and simulation engines
so i think that if we start from the low
levels and and by low levels i mean
really kind of the levels of touching
with the hardware because that's one
thing that is
very common when you're creating game
engine you have to know what
kind of hardware you're working with and
you have to understand
how the hard drive works how memory
works how gpu works how cpu works
and these kind of things that are very
common to game engines and simulation
engines because
usually for the games and for the
simulations you want to get as
much as you want from the hardware you
are developing for
so that's where on the low level the
things are
very common i can name here some kind of
a component that is
that is interacting with the file system
component that is
managing memory of course components
that are
working with the sound cards to create
some sounds
and rendering components that are
delivering some kind of a 2d or 3d
images you also have to represent
your environment or terrain whatever you
want to do in a game or the simulation
again that is a very similar component
of course it depends on how big
environments
you want to represent in the game
you also definitely want to have at
least some kind of simple physics
you need to have user interface and you
have to of course
allow the player or the trainee in the
simulation
to input somehow to control what is
happening in the 3d environment so again
there is a component for user interface
and also component for
digesting the input from from different
controls like
mouse and keyboard the another common
component would be
that you want the user of your gaming
engine or your simulation
to be able to maybe integrate it with
its third-party
libraries so for that you provide some
sdks some apis that
you can use to do that and also you want
people to be able to create their
content
that i don't mean other content now the
3d content 3d models i mean the
functionality and interaction
functionality so for that you usually
provide some kind of scripting
some kind of way of how you can program
this thing
and probably last but not least from the
very common ones
of course you need to deliver some tools
that will allow
your users to either create the 3d
content
that you want to populate your world
with
or some editors that can help you create
the training scenarios in the simulation
so these components would be the ones
that
that are very common to game engine and
the simulation engine without them you
wouldn't have
either but then you go a bit higher
level you go a bit more
offering a bit more and that's where
things start to differ between the
gaming gene
and the simulation engine because for
the gaming gene
you maybe don't need networking maybe
you do maybe you don't
so it might not come as a integral part
of the package you get
sandbox you get you might need to write
your own networking
or you buy a third-party library that
actually
for that engine provides networking same
comes with artificial intelligence there
might be some kind of a very simple
artificial intelligence included in the
game engine
but very probably you want a different
one so you will have to again
either create your own or purchase a
third-party one
so that like around these game engines
there is of course
a lot of third-party libraries and a lot
of
people and companies that are creating
these libraries then you can use
to enhance your game and to make your
game more appealing to your gamers
with the simulation engine of course
these things
have to be there also but they are very
probably
more specialized for the training use
case that the simulation delivers
so of course in our system we have an
artificial intelligence that
is very specialized for simulating
military doctrine behaviors
of different groups of soldiers that are
doing
different kinds of maneuvers we focus
on also the enemy artificial
intelligence behaviors that again
need to be somehow representing what the
soldiers can interact with
in the real world so these things start
to be very much more
focused and specialized in the
simulation engine
another example would be physics where
again in the game engine you might get
some simple physics for
calculating collisions and these kind of
things when you want to do something
more complicated
you again will probably have to write
your own in the simulation engine
you get very specialized very detailed
physics for ballistics
or for driving vehicles and all the
systems that are actually being
there on the vehicles so these like
basically when it comes to a more like
specialized functionality
that's where the components start to
differ a lot
because where for your game you might be
the simple physics for the simulation
you really need a very very complex
physics
where for the game you might need when
you're creating it for the mobile phone
to operate it with two thumbs for the
simulation you need to simulate
a very complex interaction systems that
are representing complicated
operating systems for different vehicles
and one thing that actually i haven't
seen in any gaming engine
which is actually very common for
simulations and training simulations
is something called after action review
it is a system where
which is basically being used to record
everything that is happening
during the training and then replay it
back
so the soldiers can or trainees can just
basically look
back to what they did and learn from it
and then maybe do the training again
and again and again and again look at
the after action review
in our case this is not a simple video
it is actually we're recording
everything that happens in the 3d
environment
so we can replay it again like exactly
how it happened so you can
jump in the 3d environment during the
replay see what was happening you can
pause it you can see where everybody was
what they were doing what they were
looking at
what they were aiming at so that is
something
that i have not seen in games because
you really want to return back and
replay
something so you did better there are of
course people like that
but this is something that is very very
like specialized for the simulation
cases
thanks for that comprehensive answer so
what i can summarize from that
is that you start with a gaming engine
you could start with a gaming
engine which gives you a lot of the
components you need
which is you know getting the best out
of your hardware
the user interface some of the physics
and
input device sdk scripting but then you
specialize
the algorithms the collision engine
and you further add features to record
and replay
is that a fair summary and if so did you
guys start with the gaming engine and
build upon it
that's a very good question it is a good
summary it just
of course it depends on how complicated
your simulation is
and of course how complicated your game
is because they're
again simple games and complicated games
the system that we have
here in bohemia interactive simulations
is a result of work of
more than 100 people for 10 years it's a
really really big big system
and did we start with a game engine yes
we did we had uh
actually back then we started to use a
gaming gene
that was coming from the game arma 2
which was being built by a company
bohemia interactive studio back then we
were actually assisting companies
these days we are separate companies but
yes we have started with a gaming gene
and i think that in our case it
definitely
was worth it because we got some of the
system the low-level systems
but then as i said we had to spend
10 years of many people working on
creating the functionality that then
delivers the
training and the simulation can we talk
about a couple of these areas
of specialization you know you can pick
either the
level of mathematics needed or the
collision engine
and perhaps the use of ai so
when it comes to simulation i guess that
you probably
can imagine that if you're uh teaching
people
something that then they will use in the
real world
the level of real life representation
has to be very high
like things have to be precise they have
to really
represent the real life as close as
possible so you
again don't get negative training
because if something would be
very easy because not very good physics
then you would learn that it's very easy
to do something and then
in the real life you would find out
maybe in a very bad situation that it is
not not as easy as it is so
you know for example to repair a tank
thread it's a long
process and if it would just take you
one minute in your simulation
and you learn that it's very quick then
in the real world you would be very
surprised
what all you have to do to repair a
broken tank thread
so if i should talk maybe about the
collisions and the physics
that's why we had to probably do the
most
specific changes or development
that usually is not needed in the games
and that's on the precision side because
we are currently having new engine that
is simulating the whole earth it is
rendering the whole earth
and you can just basically jump
everywhere in the world
and you would see some kind of
pre-loaded 3d environment that's
procedurally generated or you can have
actually a very real-world data in there
for that you then want to just go
anywhere in the world
from the place where you jumped in and
very
quickly when you're doing the simulation
you find out that the
normal numbers the 32-bit numbers that
are being
floating point numbers that are being
used in all of the engines
start to be very imprecise when you go
further and further from the place where
you have been
and the physics start to be which really
is uh relying on the very precise
floating numbers it starts to be very
unstable
and out of nowhere you have vehicles
that have a small bump
fly out to the space because that's how
the
floating point numbers are represented
in the pc
or in the computer so we had to switch
to
64 bit representation of these floating
point numbers
very early like many many years ago
before the games actually even started
to think about it
now because the worlds are bigger and
bigger in the games
also think about it but we had to do it
very very early to be able to just
simulate all these vast
big big environments so that would be on
the physics and
collision side on the ai side i think i
already
mentioned that we are specializing
on an ai that is that simulates the
behaviors the military behaviors so we
have to
really create a system that can handle
that and
because we are not only selling to one
army but we are
selling to many armies around the world
which have different doctrines
and they expect basically their
artificial intelligence soldiers to
behave according to that doctrine that
system has to be
like highly parameterizable so
again that that creates it uh very
complex and we spend quite a lot of time
uh doing it so these are the systems
that we had to just really spend a lot
of time on
another one is ballistics of course if
you want to have a realistic
behavior of your shells and what they do
after they explode
all the particle effects and the flashes
and these kind of things you have to
spend a lot of time
talking to the subject matter experts
who will tell you
what these things have to do and then
create the specific algorithms that can
replicate that
something you said was very interesting
is that the gaming engine is also
benefiting from all the work
that folks are doing on training engines
obtaining simulator engines
making it more real so that was
interesting to me yes definitely like i
think we are
the simulations are just kind of at
least in our case we're just pushing
what is possible
with the game engine like what is
possible to show what is possible to
represent
what is possible to interact with so i
think that we're
we're pushing the boundaries a lot maybe
more than
the games because again we need to be
very
near to the real world experience and
where some of the games of course try to
do that too
they just aspire to that they want to do
that and
if they find out that they can't get too
near they probably are okay with it
they can cut corners here and there we
can't so
definitely we're we're maybe one step
before
ahead of the gaming development let's
talk about
deployment and the specific question i
had at this point was
that multiplayer games require
cloud-based
game service is that true for
simulations as well
other use cases that you have many folks
participating
in the simulation very good question i
think i forgot to mention it when i was
talking about the components different
components of the simulation engine
training mostly is about collaboration
and cooperation
we're saying that our training is
cooperative we do not focus on training
one soldier
doing one thing on her or his own
it's just basically cooperative training
so
of course we do support multiple
trainees
being in the same scenario so some kind
of a multiplayer game
but the difference is that of course i
think
everybody knows about this massive
multiplayer online games
which as you say need a cloud based
servers and there are
hundreds of thousands of people playing
games from them
we in the simulation area are much more
like restricted and much more focused
so we always have to think about
what we are training and what is the
benefit of doing something
for the training having 100 000 trainees
in the training might not be that good
over training i'm not sure what exactly
we would be training so
currently we are focusing on hundreds of
simultaneous trained people
we are currently having customers who
are training with 200 250
trainees at once of course our customers
are thinking about how to
make these trainings bigger they are
thinking about
as i said like how the training would go
of course
if you want to go into a brigade level
that starts to be thousands of people
so of course our customers are thinking
about bringing more trainees in but
the more trainees are in the more
logistics
problems so we at this moment
uh to return back to your question we
are not having
like servers in the cloud and we're not
uh like
leveraging that functionality on the
other hand
our customers are talking to us and
we're thinking about
how we can the best actually jump on
that because we know that in the cloud
there is a future and we are thinking
about how to use
cloud to allow us to improve our
training
and it's actually currently not in the
number
of how many players we can support at
once
but it's more for us how many vehicles
really very detailed vehicles with
detailed physics we can simulate
and how many artificial intelligence
units we can have in one
training i see let's talk about the
hardware
you did mention that it is important to
get the most out of the hardware
so are there any prereqs that you have
on the client hardware
for us it's a bit more complicated than
for the gamers because
of other gaming companies because the
games
usually just come with the best graphics
and for the best graphics you
if you want to buy the latest game i
don't know cyberpunk
the gamers are like okay well i will buy
a new hardware for it because i want to
play it on the best
there's details and whatever we are
working more with
big agencies and of course the
tempo of changing the hardware is not as
fast as for the individuals
so we have to live a bit in the past we
have to support
hardware that is not the top of the
shelf hardware so we always have to
focus on not only bringing
or creating more complex simulation or
more complex environment
without thinking about how we always
also have to think about okay so
we want to do this more complex thing
but how can it work
on the hardware that is two three four
years old which again
makes the work that we're doing on the
simulation side a bit more complicated
than the for the gamers who gaming
companies which who can maybe
just basically assume that the gamers
have the latest hardware
so you have more constraints yes
we do have more constraints what about a
hardware peripherals
what are required for your simulations
joysticks vr headsets steering wheels
anything else come to mind
yes so definitely a lot of a little more
i will start with the controllers
of course joysticks like
actually some of the training is being
done with keyboard and mouse
and basically the trainees are using our
software as they would use some kind of
first person shooter
shooter game of course everything is
much more serious and they have to
adhere to the doctrine but they are
using keyboard and mouse as any player
of the
first person shooter on a pc would do
but
then of course come more complicated
scenarios and more complicated machinery
that you want to train with so
you come to joysticks steering wheels of
course
and then you start to really use very
bespoke controllers we
are integrating with pieces of hardware
that are
one-to-one replicating what you would
have in your hands inside a tank
it has all the buttons all the sounds
and all the feeling
that you would have as if you would be
sitting in the tank
so there is a lot of different
peripherals you can
actually use a simulated binoculars
into which we are actually sending the
picture so you are
using that seem like you are using a
real life
device that looks like real life
binoculars but inside you see
the image from our engine so these are
kind of things that
that we integrate with on the side of
the vr and ar devices
we are working with those for many years
now
since the first oculus not the cv one
the previous one the development kits
were released we worked with them
and we are not having only access of
course to the ones that
you can buy off the shelf we are working
with different companies that are
producing
headsets that you normally can't
buy because they're of course very
expensive but they're also very much
superior to what you can buy off the
shelf let's now talk about team and i'm
really interested in two things the
first is testing
testing is hard in this case i really
cannot
imagine how you test can you talk about
that how do you know
what you're building is actually you
know going to work
i agree that it's very complicated uh
complicated thing
and i think we have it a bit similar
with the games we rely
a lot on manual testing
so on the other hand we have also one
advantage
we have a requirements from our
customers our customers tell us what
they want to train
they tell us if they tell us hey i would
like to
train parachuting they tell us what they
expect from the training
so we of course put it into requirements
we put it into test cases
and then we turn these requirements to
test cases and then
there's a lot of manual testing being
done on those test casings making sure
that the functionality works where it
starts to be
really complicated and that is also
again
like very specific i think for what
we're doing
any new functionality has to also work
with
all the old functionality all the
previous functionality
and anything we change have to be also
backwards compatibility
backwards compatible with all the data
that were used for the previous
functionality
so we have to keep a lot of the old
code in to support previous function of
the previous type of data previous ways
of
interaction so that of course
creates immense effort when we want to
test our software which is almost
impossible we have to be always very
thorough
on if we're delivering a new release on
testing
doing this we call it regression testing
trying to find out as
many things as possible that actually
regressed from the last time we have had
a release
we have suite of automated tests you can
of course automate
some of the things i don't know you can
automate testing of
artificial intelligence so you know if
you give it some waypoint if it gets
there
if you shoot someone if it can aim and
shoot someone
but a lot of the stuff really needs a
manual testing and a very very skilled
quality assurance people so for example
for us
when we hire a new new tester it takes
several months before that person can
actually deliver
a quality results because it is so
so complicated that there is so much of
knowledge that needs to be
put into it when you're testing our
software okay so two of my takeaways
from that was that it's really really
important to get the requirements
correctly and the second was that
in spite of all that it does take time
for the qa
folks to really start you know doing a
close to perfect job as you require what
about ux designers
how do they then model the person as
and how do they get started and what is
the role of
product management here so
for the ux designers we have started
several years ago we have
basically found out that we really need
to do something on the ux side so
we have ux designers in our team because
our customers sometimes are the
procurement companies so
sometimes we do not have access to the
end users but
in many cases we do we have access to
the actual soldiers so we can ask them
what they expect or we have access to
people who will use our software to
train their soldiers
so we ask them what they expect from
what we are delivering them
how they think that it should operate we
give them some kind of
options and we try to work with them as
much as we can
in this kind of agile approach to
achieving the
goal so we constantly try to talk to
them and find out what their opinion on
the latest iteration is
that's the best case sometimes as i said
we do not have access to the
end users and then we use our internal
people we have people who
served in the military previously we
have people who have
experienced training in the military
training centers
we have people who worked as
administrators of assimilation
training facilities so we can talk to
those
and we usually try to get the best ux
design things from them
as for product management it's of course
very important
for us to somehow keep the products
going into the future in one consistent
and coherent way
that's a massive job because we are
having a lot of projects we
is another i think difference between
the simulations and the games where in
the game you
usually like really focus on one game
maybe with a big team but it
the team has one focus on this one game
we have
20 different projects for for 20
different customers
they want different ways of you want the
different new ways of
using our software for training and
that's where product management has to
look at all of these and and kind of say
okay we need to just
shape this one a bit more so it also
serves more of our customers not only
this
specific customer so that's the role of
product management making sure that what
we're doing
is reusable for as many of our customers
as possible
not to do some facebook development for
only one specific customer on the same
lines
what about the customers how do they
measure
roi that's a really complicated question
because
of course our customers use our software
to
train the soldiers and it's sometimes
very hard to find out
exactly immediately if what they're
using
if the training has a good outcome you
have to train a lot
and very often to just get some kind of
some of the skills
so we definitely talk to our customers
they are giving us feedback sometimes
we find out that some of the procedures
that are being
simulated are maybe too complicated or
the peripherals are not delivering as
much
training as they should but mostly
we have a good feedback and the most
precious feedback is
in the form of our customers telling us
that
because their soldiers were trained
using our simulator
then they got away from some very very
difficult situations in real world
scenarios and we really had a feedback
from a military personnel who told us
that because
the soldiers spent time training on our
software
they then were able to react in a
situation so that they save their lives
so
that is one of very nice feedback that
sometimes we get
but really measuring roi
is pretty complex on our software i mean
saving lives is priceless so
you know thanks for sharing that so
we'll talk a little bit later in the
show about two topics
you mentioned whole world simulation so
that sounds like an area of research and
of course
vr and motion tracking but before we get
to that
i wanted to talk to you and see if we
can work through an example
let's talk about let's say the
simulation for parallel parking
if i was a developer who wanted to
create this
how would i go about it what are my
options how would i start
so if he as a developer as a as someone
who's sitting at home and trying to
think about how to do this
i guess the fastest thing really is to
get andre
or unity or one of these engines and if
you really only
want to simulate or create a simulator
of parallel parking
and nothing more you it might be pretty
simple
using these systems to do that you just
basically place two two boxes somewhere
you would
maybe use the basic physics that comes
with these engines
and the basic car simulation that is
there and
you would place two boxes um in some
distance from each other
and then the player can just jump into
the car and try to park
and see if the player hits something or
not that would be your simple
solution for that of course things start
to be
more complicated if more requirements
come in you know
you don't want to only just train the
person to parallel park
in a very artificially created
environment you maybe want
them to learn how to park in the slope
or
when they're in the slope or you want to
train them to pearl park when there is a
traffic around them
and maybe you want to train them how to
parallel park a big
cars and small cars in the car switch
with a trailer
and the more you want to train the more
you actually are trying to starting to
find out that
it's more and more complex to make all
the new requirements to work together
and that's where you start to think
about oh
maybe i should start to look for
a simulation engine simulation solution
that would help me
fulfill all of these requirements
without me having to spend
so much time on it so to answer your
question simply if you want to do it
yourself
definitely maybe get unity unreal which
are for free and you can
quickly do something simple yourself but
if you're an
organization who for some reason
needs to teach their people or some
other people
to parallel park or in different
situations
and with different constraints maybe try
to look first
if there is any solution that would
deliver the training
already out of box i do want to dig in a
little bit more there
you know you mentioned that one of the
things you're looking for is hey do i
hit something
but you know as i'm thinking about this
what i really want to know is am i
steering correctly
you know is my car sliding well
into the slot so you can probably
approach it from
different angles and uh create different
levels of complex solutions so
the most easy one would be probably that
you would create some kind of 2d
simulation where the player would be
just operating with the arrows a box
or maybe something in the shape of a
top-down
shape of a car and you maybe know these
hints
which say that you should park next to
the car in front of you and then
go back where it's until you're half
half with the car backwards stand and
start to turn and
and you can maybe visually you can have
the player to just basically turn the
car with the keys and
with the keys on the keyboard and show
visually when to do
things when to just start to turn and
when to stop turning
so that would be the most simple thing
and you can definitely do that in the
unity
very easily with the 2d engine which is
there
i think without any additional modules
you would you would need
you then want to maybe do it a bit more
immersive
a bit more again real life like so
you would want to do it in 3d basically
placing the player into
the car and again you
can do it so that the game is being
operated by keyboard
and a mouse where you can maybe with
some keys with the keys you can operate
the car and with the mouse you can
operate the head
and uh in that case you would just
basically be able to operate your head
and look
behind you and see where you are next to
the car
in front of you and again you can
provide some kind of hints in the 3d
saying now go backwards now go backwards
so and now stop
now start to turn that wheel and you
would turn the wheel
either with the steering wheel that you
would have over the keyboard
and again the simulation can tell you
hey stop now start to back again
and stop and now change the turn of the
wheel
so you can do that again if you want to
do
this kind of a simple thing with again
with not too complicated environment
just maybe showing some simple
approximation of a street and of the
cars so that
you park in between you would be able to
do it in unreal and unity very simply
and without
any too many additions i'm not sure
about like the
basic physics that is in part of the
sandboxes but maybe you would be
even good with that and then you want to
go a bit more further as you said vr you
want to immerse the person even more
and of course with the vr you can have a
feel like freedom of moving your head
and
seeing basically everything around you
so that would create another
additional layer of immersion but for vr
you actually need much more believable
world
so you would have to spend time on maybe
creating a better
interior of your car and even the
exterior you would have to spend a bit
more time on
creating your virtual environment so
that would be
a bit more work you would have to create
this 3d content
but on the technology side again i think
it would be
pretty possible to do with the standard
unreal or unity engines which now i
think natively
support vr headsets but then it again
would get a bit more complicated
if you as i was talking about uh
previously
want to add more things in a different
traffic
different types of cars maybe different
kind of slopes and
conditions that you would need to do
parallel parking
so that's where you would maybe need a
bit more sophisticated physics to
support
different types of vehicles you will
need some kind of artificial
intelligence module
to create some pattern of life traffic
around you and you might need support
for more
comprehensive controls like even maybe a
handbrake or something like that a
clutch
if you would have a manual manual
gearbox and that starts to be
more and more complicated and you would
probably have to
do some research on what kind of
libraries exist for these engines
or you would have to build them yourself
so
really it all depends on how far
you want to go and how broadly you want
to
handle this training scenario of
parallel parking okay
so start with unity that's a perfectly
good place to start
but then as you make the scenarios more
complex you would
need to specialize the or replace the
physics engine
the ai modules and the support for
additional controls
yes the more you want to cover with your
training
the more you will very probably find
that the basic
libraries or components that are
available there for unity unreal
that they are not good enough for what
you want to achieve okay that's a good
introduction
now let's go back to what i hinted we
want to talk about
areas of research let's start with the
whole world simulation
so you said that was an important
addition
that you guys have been working on at bi
sim
so a basic question how do you do that
how do you make a replica of the whole
real world using flat images so
it's definitely not easy uh it took us
seven years oh how much
to actually come with an engine that
we're now using
for the production so basically
of course there are data that you can
use satellite images there
are now openstreetmap data which you can
access and get and all the data is
actually georeferenced so they from
openstreetmap
you can get vectors that are
representing streets
or building or footprints of buildings
in the real world coordinates so
you can actually place them there where
they should be
the complex thing is how to
get all the data into the memory of a pc
so that it looks as good as it can
and it still performs very well that's
the biggest challenge there how
do you represent the whole world
terrain geometry in the memory
how do you represent it so that you can
actually fit it into the memory
like in places where you want to create
a training so there are many many
sophisticated algorithms for that that
are of course around the area of
level of detail uh loading where we had
to just basically create some bespoke
algorithms to cope with that of course
we are not having all the data at once
in the memory we're
very cleverly streaming the data in
there where you want to have the image
from we also
like you can again get a data which
represent the height map
or the basically how high things are in
the real world
how high above the sea they are you can
get the data
that they are publicly accessible or you
can buy them in a different types of
precision again maybe you get to
precision of one meter or maybe 10
meters
that data is maybe even publicly
accessible or
kind of cheap but if you want to get
into the precision of millimeters
then again the daytime might not even
exist any day with exit state would be
very very very expensive so
again we had to come up with algorithms
that
we call process refinement refine the
data that we have maybe 10 meter
precision so you only have basically
vertex every 10 meters
so you can't for example do trenches or
something like that or ditches because
you would have to do only ditches that
are 10 meters wide
so we're coming with these algorithms
for refinement of the terrain so that we
can go
under centimeter precision and that
allows us to do very very refined
modifications to the terrain in case we
like customers wanted to
build some trenches or want to have a
very specific
representation or very real life
specification of the terrain
so that is the biggest challenge how to
get all of the data how to store it so
that
it is very quickly accessible and then
when you access it how to put it into
the memory so it can be displayed in a
very efficient way
so you still have 100 fps 120
frames per second when you're moving
through the environment
as you have in the normal games it's
really fascinating and i can imagine
really really challenging
what about motion tracking for vr
i imagine that's absolutely critical for
realistic simulations as well can we
talk a little bit about that
when i hear motion tracking i kind of
think about this complicated
tracking of all your joints and all your
limbs and your head
we do not have to get that complex most
of the times
we have customers who want that who want
to just basically
track the motion of the soldiers and we
provide
solutions for that for the vr
it's actually not that complex because
the headsets usually come with
their inbuilt ways of tracking the
motion of the head
they also come with very clever
algorithms to
prevent people from getting motion sick
if the screen is not
updating as quickly as possible so
that kind of a tracking of the head for
the vr headsets is not that much of a
complication for us because
the headsets usually come up with a good
sdks that provide us all the information
that we need
let's start to wrap up now is there any
topic
that you want to talk about that we
haven't touched on today
not specifically i hope that the session
somehow is able to deliver the message
that simulations
are different to uh even if we started
with a gaming engine
we are now really really very different
to what a game would be
on the other hand as i already said if
you would probably see
you know some of our customers training
their soldiers somewhere in the facility
you would get there and they would be
sitting there
using their keyboard and mouse and you
would say well they're playing a game
then you would have to observe what is
happening around that they
might be you might think that they're
playing a game but everything has a
really
very strict rules and it is for us it's
very
important to not deliver a negative
training and that's uh that's what we do
that's what we try to achieve to make
something that
really delivers a very very good
training so
anyone who is using our software is then
getting out
prepared for what can be ahead of them
in the real
world so i would say that the biggest
difference uh
if we should talk about like if i should
close on the topic of
difference between a game engine as i
described it at the start
and the full simulation engine it's the
vast
amount of work that is being spent on
the simulation engine so it can deliver
the training that it needs to i did
watch some of the videos
of bi sim on the youtube channel and i
did find them fascinating
you know leveraging all the efforts and
all the success that gaming engine has
done
and channeling that into training
you know it is definitely something that
i hope our listeners
find as interesting as i did and talking
to you today as well
how can people contact you so people can
contact me on my
email address if they want to contact me
it's a simple autocad.neter
fbisimulations.com they can of course go
to our web page
and contact our company through some of
the contacts that i mentioned that that
might be
the best way because of course i am a
bit busy so i might not be just
answering quickly so i think the best
way would be to go to our web pages
which is bisimulations.com
and search for the contacts information
there
we'll put a link to that in the show
notes thank you so much
for being with us today arka it was an
awesome session thank you
thank you for inviting me and thank you
for your great questions
this is kanjin shrinky for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening